<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General | X1B Plan]]></title>
  <link href="http://tswann.github.io/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tswann.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-04T16:43:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://tswann.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tom Swann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BirdTrack and the power of Citizen Science]]></title>
    <link href="http://tswann.github.io/blog/2013/05/31/birdtrack-and-the-power-of-citizen-science/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-31T13:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tswann.github.io/blog/2013/05/31/birdtrack-and-the-power-of-citizen-science</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been on a bit of a hiatus as regards the blog over the last month. Becoming a father, and simultaneously a zombified version of my former self are the prime cause.</p>

<p>Occasionally the volume of coffee hits just the correct tipping point such that I can string two thoughts together and hold them for just long enough that typing can happen. Now is that time.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about <a href="http://blx1.bto.org/birdtrack">BirdTrack</a> lately &ndash; a website and app from the <a href="http://www.bto.org/">BTO</a> which allow members of the public to submit their sightings of birds. It&rsquo;s a fine case of technology, a desperate need and a willing public all combining to achieve great things. To borrow some parlance from the mighty <a href="http://www.rockpapershotgun.com/">RPS</a>, this post is <strong>Wot I Think</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>Before it is too late, I have tried to recapture the extraordinary beauty of this bird and to convey the wonder of the land he lived in, a land to me as profuse and glorious as Africa. It is a dying world, like Mars, but glowing still.</p>

<ul>
<li>J A Baker, <em>The Peregrine</em></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>Written in 1967, John Bakers masterpiece of nature writing &lsquo;The Peregrine&rsquo;, is a deeply personal and lyrical account of his years spent tracking and studying the falcons across the farmland and estuaries of his native Essex.</p>

<p>At that time the Peregrine falcon was undergoing a catastrophic decline in the United Kingdom (and elsewhere), owing largely to use of the <a href="http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1948/">pesticide DDT</a> a substance which is particularly harmful for those birds at the top of the food chain in whom it accumulates.</p>

<p>A concentrated conservation effort and bans on harmful pesticides brought the Peregrine back from the brink of extinction in the UK &ndash; the fate which Baker had so feared for the bird.</p>

<p>For every Pheonix there are others which have not been so lucky. The <a href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/ourwork/science/stateofnature/index.aspx">State of Nature report</a> which was published earlier this month carried the grave headline that 60% of native animal species assessed had suffered a decline in the past 50 years. 31% have suffered a &lsquo;strong&rsquo; decline.</p>

<p>I was fortunate enough to grow up in an area of mid-Antrim where there was a great profusion of some of our most iconic species.</p>

<p>I say <em>was</em> rather pointedly. In my lifetime the Curlew, Lapwing and Hen Harrier have all slowly followed the Corncrake (a bird of my parents' generation) on the road to local extinction. They are not there yet &ndash; but if there is not a collective will to prevent it, then it will be inevitable.</p>

<h2>BirdTrack</h2>

<p>In light of such a grim assessment, what can ordinary people &ndash; people who are not professionally involved in conservation efforts I suppose &ndash; contribute to help prevent species from declining?</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s often said that there are two ways to vote &ndash; with your money or with your time. We technologists should be well familiar with this idea. The shiniest tech always gets carried along on a wave of popular enthusiasm.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Citizen Science&rdquo; taps in to this tendency of clever and enthusiastic people to vote with their time and effort.</p>

<p>I first came to BirdTrack some years ago whilst randomly browsing the BTOs site. A web app that allowed the public to sign up and submit their own detailed bird observations. I found this to be an incredibly simple idea &ndash; why had no one thought of this sooner!</p>

<p>After years of operation the site has become an absolute trove of interesting and important data. Yearly trends in the reporting rates of individual species; earliest recordings of spring migrants; maps of regional distribution&hellip; there is all this and more. When I log on to the Android app I am presented with a map showing sightings that others have recorded in the vicinity of wherever I am. It truly is a fantastic tool for anyone interested in birds &ndash; if they&rsquo;d had this back in my formative years I would have been all over it!</p>

<p>As well as tapping into the natural tendency in birders to meticulously list everything they see, it also throws in a few modern &lsquo;gamification&rsquo; twists as well. There are leader boards for total species in a year, total lists submitted in a month&hellip; the dedication of some people is truly staggering.</p>

<h2>Why This Is Important</h2>

<p>Jennifer Pahlka delivered an excellent talk available on <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/jennifer_pahlka_coding_a_better_government.html">TED</a> called <em>&lsquo;Coding A Better Government&rsquo;</em>. It&rsquo;s a popular one among tech evangelists who like to believe that many problems of governmental bureaucracy can be overcome by using technology to empower citizens.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an apt lesson that conservation can learn from as well. BirdTrack is a shining example of how much can be achieved when you put a powerful tool in people&rsquo;s hands.</p>

<p>If you are interested in contributing, you can sign up at <a href="http://blx1.bto.org/birdtrack">http://blx1.bto.org/birdtrack</a>. There are also a variety of other surveys being run on the BTO website at any given time.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bto.org/shop/bird-atlas">2007 &ndash; 2011 Bird Atlas</a> is also available for pre-order &ndash; a project which owes it&rsquo;s existence in large part to the efforts of volunteers through BirdTrack and the BTOs other national surveys.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/47685018/Blog/2013/06-01/theperegrine.jpg" alt="The Peregrine" /></p>

<p>Glowing still.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
